现在我们对内核堆的工作原理有了一些了解
now that we have some idea of how the kernel heap works
我们来看一些
let's take a look at some of the
内核堆保护机制
kernel heap Protection mechanisms
它们可以编译到内核中
that can be compiled into the kernel
使攻击者更难以利用内核漏洞
to make it more difficult for an attacker to exploit it
第一个值得一提的保护机制
now the first mitigation that is worth mentioning
就是所谓的空闲链表随机化
is something that's called freelist randomization
默认情况下
by default
当创建一个新的slab时
when a fresh slab is created
空闲列表默认是有序的
the free list will default to being in order
我说的“有序”是什么意思呢
what I mean when I say in order
对于一个新的slab
is for a fresh slab
第一个被分配出去的slot
the first slot that will be used to satisfy an allocation
会是slab上的第一个slot
will be the first slot on the slab
第二次调用kmalloc或kmem_cache_alloc时
then with a for instance kmalloc or kmem_cache_alloc were called a second time
总之第二次从这个slab中分配内存时
that drew from this slab
将把第二个slot分配出去
the second allocation would come from the second slot
第三次分配会分配出去第三个slot
the third allocation would come from the third slot
这是有序的
this would be in order
默认情况下新的slab的分配是有序的
the kind of default freelist is in order for a brand new slab
这对攻击者是有利的
now this is beneficial to an attacker
因为攻击者很容易得知
because an attacker can easily know
内存中已分配对象之间的位置关系
where in memory allocated objects relate to each other
一般说来
in generally speaking
攻击者的目标是在内存中获得两个相邻的对象
an attacker's goal is to get two objects right next to each other in memory
或者在内存中有预谋地放置对象
or to strategically place objects in memory
比如有一些属性
such that there is some property
但攻击者进攻的关键
but the kind of key for the attacker
就是知道这些已分配对象在内存中的位置
is to know where these objects are being allocated in memory
然后利用这些位置之间的关系
to then take advantage of the relationship between those locations
把这些对象按顺序排列
so by having this in order
攻击者就很容易知道
it's easy for an attacker to know
新slab上分配对象之间的关系
the relationship between allocations on a fresh slab
freelist随机化
so freelist randomization
就像名字说的
does exactly kind of what the name implies
freelist随机化配置选项
the freelist randomization configuration option
会随机化freelist
randomizes the freelist
有什么效果呢
so what is the impact here
对于一个新的slab
for a fresh slab
你无法得知哪个slot会被返回
you have no guarantees about which slot will be returned
以满足那些最先从这个slab分配内存的请求
for those initial allocations that are drawing from the slab
因此，第一次可能分配出去了slot 0
so the first allocation may draw from slot 0
第二次可能分配出去了slot 14
but then the second allocation may draw from slot 14
就是我们这里看到的
which is what we see here
第三次针对这个slab的请求
the third allocation against this slab
可能分配出去slot 16
maybe that draws from slot 16
针对一个新的slab的初始分配顺序是随机的
the order of the initial allocations against a fresh slab is randomized
这种随机化的实现方式
now the way that this randomization is done
是在最开始针对该cache
is for the cache initially
生成一个随机化的索引列表random_seq
a random_seq of indexes is generated
这些索引都是整数
these indexes are integers
它们存储在kmem_cache.random_seq
and they are stored in the kmem_cache.random_seq location
作为kmem_cache的一个链表成员
so it's stored as a member of the kmem_cache as a linked list
这就是这个链表
and so there's this linked list
它表示默认freelist的顺序
that represents the order of the default freelist order
但是回想一下，空闲链表本质上是一个单链表
but recall that the free list is essentially a singly linked list
这个单链表添加空闲对象时，用的头插法
and freed objects of a singly linked list are pushed to the head of the list
在创建slab时顺序会随机化一次
now the order may be randomized once at slab creation
在slab第一次出现的时候是随机化的
when the slab is first brought in
但如果攻击者有能力分配许多对象
but if an attacker has the ability to allocate many objects
比如攻击者可以分配完整个slab
then the attacker can allocate the entire slab let's say
之后攻击者可以按照自己想要的顺序释放它们
and then the attacker could free them in whatever order the attacker desires
这意味着攻击者可以决定空闲列表的顺序
and that means that the attacker can determine the order of the free list
或者说攻击者可以设置空闲列表的顺序
or the attacker can set the order of the free list
根据攻击者释放分配对象的顺序，来决定它的顺序
based upon the order that the attacker frees the objects that were allocated previously
这对攻击者来说仍然是一个挑战
now this still presents a challenge to the attacker
因为攻击者可能能分配所有这些对象
because the attacker may be able to allocate all of these objects
但是攻击者不知道
but the attacker doesn't know by default
默认情况这些对象是如何相互关联的
how these objects relate to each other
这就给攻击者带来了额外的挑战
and so this creates an additional challenge for the attacker
因为攻击者
because the attacker
必须使用其他类型的漏洞
must use some other type of vulnerability
来弄清楚这些内核对象是如何相互关联的
to figure out how these kernel objects relate to each other
因为在典型的漏洞利用场景中
because in a typical exploitation scenario here
攻击者不在内核中
the attacker isn't in the kernel
所以攻击者不能获取这些原始指针
so the attacker isn't the one that is getting these raw pointers
攻击者不是获取这些内核对象的人
the attacker isn't the one that is obtaining these kernel objects
相反，攻击者只是促使内核分配这些内核对象
instead the attacker is encouraging the kernel to allocate these kernel objects
攻击者通常在用户空间的某个地方
the attacker is typically somewhere in userland
他们使用
and they are using
例如syscall
for instance syscalls
或通过ioctl使用内核设备
or they're calling ioctl on a kernel device
内核设备触发内核内的内存申请
and that is triggering the allocations inside of the kernel
这样攻击者就看不到
and so the attacker doesn't get to see
对象的原始内存地址
the raw memory addresses of the object
攻击者只知道他们确实创建了一个对象
the attacker just knows that they did create an object
基于他们触发了内核内的哪种东西
based upon what they have triggered inside of the kernel to occur
那么攻击者怎么弄清楚
so how does an attacker figure out
这些内存分配之间的关系
how these allocations relate to each other
攻击者可以
well the attacker can
依靠我们在前面堆内容中看到的策略
rely on a strategy that we've seen in earlier heap content
例如，攻击者可以依靠UAF
an attacker can rely on for instance a use after free bug
如果攻击者有指向空闲slot的指针
if the attacker has a pointer into a freed slot
这个slot不是空闲列表的最后一个slot
and that slot is not the last slot of the free list
那么这个slot将包含一个next指针
then that slot is going to contain a next pointer
所以在UAF的情况下
so in a use after free scenario
攻击者可以构建这里展示的利用原语
the attacker can build a primitive as shown here
攻击者有一个指针，例如指向slot0
where the attacker has a pointer to for instance slot 0
slot0里有一个next指针
which slot 0 contains a next pointer
它记录了slot1的地址（用UAF获得了slot1的地址）
that identifies the address of slot 1
然后攻击者可以malloc两次
the attacker could then malloc twice
然后释放slot2
and then for instance free slot 2
然后释放slot0
then free slot zero
然后用相同的原语
then use this same primitive
读取slot2的地址
to read the address of slot 2
此时
at which point
攻击者知道了这两个分配之间的关系
now the attacker knows the relationship between those two allocations
因为他们可以比较泄露的这两个地址的距离
because they can compare the distance between the two pointers that were read
因此，UAF对攻击者来说是很好的
so a use after free scenario would be great for an attacker
但内核还有另一种保护机制
but the kernel has another mitigation strategy
这使得这种情况更加困难
that makes this scenario more difficult
这就是所谓的freelist加固
and that is something that's called freelist hardening
在我描述前面的情况时
when I describe the scenario here above
用UAF泄漏next指针
with the use after free and kind of leaking next pointers
希望这能让你们回想起
hopefully this reminded you a little bit about
tcache的链表是如何工作的
how tcache's linked list works
因为这仍然是一个依赖于next指针的单链表
because it is still a singly linked list that relies on next pointers
tcache是如何保护next指针的
and how did tcache protect next pointers
他使用了一种叫safe linking的东西
tcache used something that was called safe linking
用一个特定的值与next异或，来模糊它
where they xor specific values with the pointer to obscure it
这样如果next指针
so that way if the next pointer
被攻击者看到
happened to be visible or leaked to an attacker
泄露的值不会提供任何有用的信息
the initial value that's leaked doesn't provide any useful information
freelist加固的工作原理与tcache的safe linking非常相似
well freelist hardening works very similar to safelinking on the tcache side
思路是用一些值和next指针异或
the logic is we're going to xor some values with the pointer
这应该会模糊它
and this should obscure it
使它在功能上对攻击者无用
to make it functionally useless to the attacker
safe linking在异或时有一个有趣的机制
now safe linking had kind of an interesting mechanism as far as how the xoring was done
与next异或的值是next的地址右移12位
it was the pointer with the address of the pointer bit shifted
我们在tcache模块中肯定见过这个
and we definitely took a look at that in the tcache module
freelist加固的工作方式略有不同
the freelist hardening works slightly differently as far as
究竟是怎么模糊next的
what is exactly occurring to obscure the pointer
不再做位左移了
instead of doing some bit shifting
会有3个值异或
there are three values that are being xored
next自己
there's the pointer itself
next的地址
there's the address of the pointer
还有一个随机的cache相关值
and then there is a random cache specific value
它来引入随机性
which is just referred to as random
我们在代码片段中看到
and we see here in the code snippet
这个随机值在kmem_cache中
that random is attached to the kmem_cache
所以这个随机值是kmem_cache的成员
so there's this random value that is a member of the kmem_cache
这个随机值
and that random value
会和next指针异或
is xored with the pointer
以及next指针的地址异或
as well as the address of the pointer
这样就能模糊next指针
and so that this would obscure it
所以现在攻击者不能用这个原语了
so now the attacker can't work just off of this primitive
或者他们能
or can they
我们来思考一下这里发生了什么
well let's think a little bit about what's going on here
情况是这样的
so here's our scenario
攻击者有和之前相同UAF
and the attacker has that same use after free primitive
攻击者能泄露什么呢
well what can the attacker leak
在这个情况下
well in this scenario
攻击者可以泄漏编码后的值
the attacker can leak the encoded value
就是我们在这里看到的
which is what we saw right here
编码后的值就是
the encoded value is the pointer
指针异或上指针地址
xored with the pointer's address
再异或上一个随机值
xored with the random value
在这种情况下
and so in this scenario
就是之前的情况
which is where we were earlier
攻击者可以读取指针与指针地址和随机值的异或结果
the attacker can read address of pointer xored with pointer xored with random
不是特别有用
not particularly useful
但是攻击者可以识别出
but what an attacker can recognize
如果有UAF
they can if they have a use after free
并且他们有能力影响
and they have the ability to influence
空闲列表的状态
the kind of state of the free list
他们就可以创造这样的场景
they can create this scenario
如果UAF指针的next为null
what happens if the use after free's next pointer is null
这和我们最初的情况非常相似
it's very similar to what we had initially
如果我们创建一个next为null的场景
if we were to create the scenario where there is no pointer value
那么攻击者可以读出，指针地址异或上随机值的结果
then the attacker can read the address of the pointer xored with the random value
这两个单独拿出来都没有用
now neither of these are useful really on their own
这么说并不完全正确
well that's not entirely true
它两单独拿出来都没法帮攻击者弄清slot地址
but they don't help the attacker know the location of any of the slots on their own
但放在一起
but together
这两个值
these two values
能让攻击者泄露next指针
allow the attacker to reveal that pointer
首先得到的是
so the first thing that they can obtain is
这个场景中被模糊的next指针
this obscured pointer from this scenario here
第二个可以得到的是
the second thing that the attacker could obtain
我们让next指针为null的结果
is what if we made the pointer null right
我们这样设置
we set it up such that
UAF指向的slot是空闲列表中最后的一个
the use after free is the last item in the free list
在这种情况下，它的next指针为空
in which case its next pointer is null
那么攻击者就可以得到它
well then the attacker can obtain that
指针地址异或上随机值的结果
address of the pointer xored with the random value
如果攻击者可以获得这两个
if the attacker can obtain both of these
那攻击者就能将它们异或
then the attacker could xor them together
此时攻击者就得到了next指针
at which point the attacker has revealed the pointer
这就足够了
and so that is sufficient
不仅仅是能解码一个模糊后的值
not only to decode an obscured value
就像我们刚刚展示的
which is what we've just shown right here
同时这里第二个值
but this second value right here
指针地址 ^ nulll ^ 随机值
the address of pointer xored with null xored with random
足以用它去编码一个next指针
is sufficient to encode a pointer
这就是攻击者需要的一切
and so this is everything an attacker needs
就可以影响空闲列表
to influence the free list
既可以解码出空闲列表中slot的位置
to either reveal the location of slots that are on the freelist
也可以更改空闲列表中slot的next指针
or overwrite pointers on the freelist
控制从该cache返回的内存地址
to redirect what values will be returned from requesting an allocation from this cache
攻击者可能利用的另一个场景
another scenario that attacker may take advantage of
是越界访问场景
is an out of bounds access scenario
我们看一下我们设置了什么
so let's take a look at what we have set up here
如果slab的构造是这样的
well what if the slab is configured such that
有一个被分配的有效对象
there is a valid object that is allocated
有一个合法的指针指向这个对象
and there's a valid pointer to this object because it was allocated
紧接着这个合法对象
now immediately after the valid object
正好有一个空闲slot
there happens to be a free slot
当这个空闲slot恰好有一个next指针时
when this free slot happens to contain a next pointer
这个next指针可能有被编码
now this next pointer could be encoded
此时攻击者必须
at which point the attacker has to
进行前面描述的步骤
involve the steps that were described earlier
但我们先假定它没被编码
but right now let's imagine that it's not encoded
数据传输的典型方式
well the way that data is typically transferred
从用户空间到内核，或从内核到用户空间
from userland to the kernel or from kernel to userland
通过函数copy_to_user或copy_from_user
is via the functions copy_to_user or copy_from_user
那么，如果这个对象会
so what if this object is supposed to be in normal functionality
复制到用户空间，或从用户空间复制到内核
copied to userland or copied from userland to the kernel
如果攻击者不操纵指针
well if the attacker instead of manipulating the pointers that are involved
而是以某种方式控制拷贝的字节数
somehow gains control of the number of bytes to copy
那攻击者可以访问或影响
then the attacker can access or influence
该内核对象以外的数据
bytes that are outside of the kernel object that was allocated
那当攻击者能复制超出预计长度的数据到用户空间
so in the event the attacker can copy to the user more than the intended number of bytes
会发生什么?
what would happen
如果正常可以复制整个对象
well the attacker would be able to copy this entire object
然后假设攻击者设法把长度翻倍了
and then let's say that they somehow manage to double it
那他会泄露出整个对象，外加
well they would leak this entire object plus
内存中下一个对象的所有字节
all of the bytes of the object that is next in memory here
在内存中相邻的
that follows it in memory
按这个例子
in this case
我们会泄漏位于slot1中的对象
we would be leaking the object that is located in slot 1
以及空闲slot2的所有数据
as well as all of the bytes of the freed slot 2
在这个例子中，它包含一个next指针
and in this case that contains a next pointer
现在攻击者获得了一些
and so now the attacker has gained some information
关于这个slab中正在使用的地址的信息
about the addresses that are being used in this slab
如果攻击者可以做相反的事情呢
now what if the attacker can do the reverse
攻击者可以从用户空间复制到内核
and the attacker can copy from userland to the kernel
这种情况
so this would be a scenario
内核对象会装一些用户空间数据
where the kernel object is intended to contain some userland data
我们再假设攻击者
and again let's pretend that the attacker
设法将拷贝的长度翻了一倍
somehow manages to double the size of that copy
那么攻击者就可以写入整个对象
well then the attacker can write this entire object
外加后面这个空闲slot
plus all of the bytes of the freed slot after
这样的话
and if that is the case
攻击者可以覆盖next指针
then the attacker can overwrite this next pointer
这会影响
which would then influence
以后这个slab返回的内存地址
what pointers would be returned from future allocations against this slab
这是一个一般的越界访问场景
so this is a general out of bounds access scenario
我们描述了越界读和越界写
we described both in out of bounds read as well as an out of bounds write
对于那些要用对象
for those objects that are intended to be used
在用户空间和内核之间拷贝数据的
for copying data between userland and the kernel
可以配置一种保护机制
there's an additional mitigation that can be configured
称为用户拷贝加固
called Hardened Usercopy
这些有问题的拷贝进或出内核
so these mistaken copying back and forth from the kernel
能导致这些越界访问或信息泄露
can result in these out of bound accesses or information being leaked
这不是想要的
that wasn't intended
这个保护机制使得
what this mitigation enables
cache中增加了2个成员
is the cache now has an additional two members
一个 offset变量
it has an offset member
和一个 size变量
and it has a size value
这两个值代表了
and these two values represent the region of memory
在这片内存中
that is allowed to be copied
允许在用户空间和内核之间拷贝的范围
and transferred back and forth from user land to the kernel
所以这些值可以用来校验
so these values can be used to verify
进出内核的数据
that the bytes that are being transferred to and from the kernel
是否在预计范围内
are within the intended range
我们可以看看它是什么样子的
we can take a look at what that looks like
所以在前面这里
so up above here
有这个内核对象
we had this kernel object
我们说
and we said well
它们可以复制整个内核对象
they could copy this entire kernel object
如果不能从开头拷贝数据
well what if instead of starting the copy at the beginning
该内核对象的正常使用方法
the intended use of this kernel object
是只能拷贝整个内核对象的一小部分
was to just copy a small sub section of the entire kernel object
我们可以用offset和size来定义它
well we can define that with these offset and size values
如果这里是对象的起点
where if this is the start of the object
我们不能拷贝
we can't copy anything between the start of the object
对象起点到起点+offset之间的东西
and the start of the object plus offset
我们不能拷贝
and we can't copy anything
起点+offset+size后的
past the size added to the offset added to the start of the object
我们只能拷贝
so we are only allowed to copy
这个区域内的
this region shown right here
如果攻击者能够操纵写入大小
if somehow the attacker was able to manipulate these values
让copy_to_user或copy_from_user
so that copy_to_user or copy_from_user
访问了内核对象规定范围之外的内存
was accessing a memory outside of this specifically defined range of the kernel object
那么它就会失败
then it would fail
这行得通的原因是
the reason that this can work
正如你记得的
is because a cache as you'll recall
cache中的slot大小是固定的
is created with a specific size slot in mem
我们在这里做的是，在创建cache时
so what we're doing here is we're creating a cache
不光规定了slot大小
not only with a specific size slot in mem
还设置了一个特定的对象
but we're creating a cache with a specific object in mem
偏移量和大小值存储在kmem_cache结构体中
and the offset and size values are stored inside the kmem_cache struct
这意味着所有依据这个cache分配的内核对象
so that means that all kernel objects that are allocated against the cache
都会启用用户拷贝加固检查
will have this hardened user copy check occur
如果正确实现了这个，攻击者该怎么做呢
so what does an attacker do if this is properly implemented
攻击者感兴趣的内核对象启用了用户拷贝加固
in the kernel objects that the attacker is interested in have hardened usercopy
它们是从正确启用了这个的cache中分配的
and they're being allocated against a cache that is properly employing this
攻击者会考虑
well what an attacker would question
这些值究竟是在哪里检查的
is well where exactly are these values being checked
我一开始描述这种情况时提到的一件事
well one of the things that I mentioned when I kind of initially described this scenario
copy_to_user和copy_from_user
was well copy_to_user and copy_from_user
算是
are kind of the default ways
用户空间和内核之间传递数据的默认方式
that data is transferred from userland to the kernel and from kernel to userland
这基本是正确的
and that is broadly speaking true
在copy_from_user和copy_to_user内
inside copy_from_user and copy_to_user
会调用kmem_cache_create_usercopy
they call kmem_cache_create_usercopy
这时会拷贝数据
and so they separate copy is created
在这个过程中会调用__check_heap_object
and during that process __check_heap_object is called
你可以看一下Linux源代码
you can definitely check out the Linux source
如果你想看一下这个调用栈
if you want to follow the call stack here
这个__check_heap_object
but this __check_heap_object
会对这些值进行比较和验证
is where these values are actually compared and verified
如果调用了copy_from_user
and so if copy_from_user is utilized
校验会发生
the check will happen
如果使用了copy_to_user
if copy_to_user is used
校验会发生
the check will happen
但不是所有拷贝内存的操作
but not all operations that copy memory
都校验这些值
verify these values
例如
for example
如果
what happens if
没用标准的copy_from_user和copy_to_user
instead of using kind of the approved standard of copy_from_user and copy_to_user
内核中有些功能使用了memcpy
there is functionality in the kernel that uses memcpy
memcpy不知道要去这里
memcpy has no idea that it's supposed to go
查看slab分配器的cache
and look at a slab allocators cache
找到偏移量和大小
and then find this offset and size
然后做一些校验
and do some type of verification step
memcpy只知道
memcpy just
我要从这里开始
here's where I start
拷贝这么多
here's how far I go
到某个地方
copy go brr
好的
right
所以攻击者会找内核中
and so an attacker would be very interested in finding locations in the kernel
从用户空间到内核
that copy from userland to the kernel
或者从内核到用户空间
or from kernel to userland
在拷贝时用的这两种方法之外的其他方法
via other methods than these two
这种情况确实存在
and these certainly do exist
我要讲的最后一个保护机制
the last mitigation that I'm going to talk about
是我们应该很熟悉的东西
is something that we should already be familiar with
就是KASLR
and that's KASLR
它代表内核地址空间布局随机化
which stands for Kernel Address Space Layout Randomization
KASLR的工作原理与用户空间的ASLR非常相似
now KASLR works very similar to userland ASLR
ASLR是做什么的
in the sense that what does ASLR do
ASLR会随机化内存地址中的一些字节
ASLR randomizes some bytes in memory addresses
这使得攻击者难以知道
which makes it more difficult for an attacker to know
东西在内存中的位置
where things are located in memory
用户空间的ASLR
now in Userland ASLR
每次执行一个新进程，就随机化一次
these addresses are randomized every time we execute a new process
内核内存空间不能重新随机化
but we don't have that same opportunity to re-randomize with kernel memory
因为内核内存
because the kernel memory
在系统启动的时候就建立好了
gets kind of stood up when the system first starts up
我们不能在运行时重新随机化
we can't re-randomize in the middle of running
因此KASLR只在每次启动时将这些地址随机化
and so KASLR randomizes these addresses per boot
这些地址被随机化，或说得到它们的随机字节
the addresses are randomized or obtain their randomized bytes
发生在系统启动时
when the system first starts up
从启动到关机它一直是一个常量
and it's going to be a constant from the time that the system has booted until the system shuts down
然后下次系统启动时，它会被重新随机化
and then it would be re-randomized next time the system starts up
攻击者对抗KASLR的策略
now the attacker's general strategy for combating KASLR
和对抗ASLR是一样的
is the exact same thing as combating ASLR
就是找到一个信息泄露漏洞
the strategy is get a leak
知道一个地址
where you know what it is
计算到基址
compute an offset to a base address
然后
and then
基于那个基址
based on that base address
你可以知道东西在内存中的位置
you can suddenly know where things are located in memory
那么如何从内核得到泄漏呢
so how do you get a leak from the kernel
一种泄露方式是
one way that you can get a leak
利用所谓的内核oops
is by taking advantage of something that is known as a kernel oops
内核运行时当然会遇到错误
so the kernel certainly can encounter errors right
可能有一个不好的内核模块
there could be a bad kernel module
我们不希望每次出现一个小bug
and we don't want the kernel to drastically fail
内核就直接崩溃
every time a small bug occurs
所以如果内核遇到错误
so if the kernel encounters an error
只要识别出是非致命的
that it recognizes is non fatal
它将试图从中恢复
it will attempt to recover from it
如果内核设置成
if the kernel is configured
oops消息输出
such that oops messages will be output
错误的详细信息
the error details
包括寄存器信息
including the register information
都可以通过dmesg命令打印出来
will be printed out inaccessible via dmesg
所以你可以在dojo虚拟机上运行dmesg
so on the dojo Vms you could run dmesg
然后在虚拟机外面
and then from outside the vm
我推荐在外面
which is what I'd encourage
你可以用vm logs命令查看相同的信息
you can see that same information by using the vm logs command
所以通过在内核内触发一个非致命错误
and so by triggering an error inside of the kernel that's non fatal
内核认为它可以恢复的错误
that the kernel identifies as something it can recover from
就可以泄漏寄存器信息
it can leak register information
包括内核地址
including kernel addresses
如果内核地址碰巧在错误发生时存储在寄存器中的话
if a kernel address happens to be stored in a register at the time of the error
内核也可以设置成遇到oops情况时panic
now the kernel can also be configured to panic on oops
什么是内核恐慌
now what's a kernel panic
内核oops是指遇到的错误非致命
well a kernel oops was if the error was non fatal
例如，它是某种类型的内存访问错误
it was for instance some type of memory access
在内核中识别到
in the kernel just identified
我们正在尝试访问一个无效的内存地址
we're trying to access an invalid memory address
我们不需要使整个内核崩溃
we don't need to fail the entire kernel
我们只需要报告这个错误就可以
we just need to report this error and we can
我们可以继续运行
we can carry out
我们可以从这个错误中恢复过来
we can recover from this error
这触发的就是一个oops
that is what triggers an oops
但如果一个错误是灾难性的
but if an error is so catastrophic
内核无法从中恢复
that the kernel isn't capable of recovering from it
那么内核就会panic
then the kernel will do something that's called kernel panic
内核panic与oops非常相似
kernel panic is very similar to an oops
在都会输出错误信息这方面
in the sense that an error message can be output
但panic输出信息后，系统会锁住无法继续执行
but then the system essentially locks up and execution cannot continue
内核识别到进入了无法恢复的状态
the kernel identifies that it is entered a non recoverable state
它就停止运作了
and it ceases to operate
这就是所谓的内核panic（吓呆了）
and this is what's known as a kernel panic
内核可以设置成
now the kernel can be configured
将原来遇到非致命错误时输出oops消息
so that these non fatal errors that typically output in oops
改成内核panic
will instead result in a kernel panic
在这种情况下
in that type of a scenario
让内核泄漏内核地址要困难得多
it's a lot harder to get the kernel to leak kernel addresses
因为不能触发oops机制了
because we no longer have this kind of oops mechanism to trigger that
有一件事要记住
one thing to keep in mind
内核会响应所有的进程
is that the kernel responds to all processes
有一些panic检查
and some of the panic checks
发生在某个特定进程
occur within the context of a specific process
比如我有一个过程
so like if I had a process
它故意向内核中注入非法地址
that is deliberately injecting bad addresses into the kernel
并让内核解引用它
and then causing the kernel to dereference them
这样内核可以识别到
that is something that the kernel could identify
这个进程打算利用这些坏地址
this process intends to utilize these bad addresses
这个进程打算访问这些坏地址
and this process intends on accessing these bad addresses
内核可以识别
the kernel can identify
回顾之前的执行
you look back at previous execution
并确定其意图
and kind of identify the intent
这注定要发生了
and say that this is clearly what was meant to happen
是无法恢复了
and this is unrecoverable
但一些panic检查是可以避免的
but some of these panic checks may be avoided
如果不是全都在一个进程中做
if instead of doing all of that in one process
触发非法访问的
the triggering access
在一个单独的进程
occurs in a separate process
而不是在建立的进程
than the process that's setting up
我故意在这里说得有点模糊
I'm purposely being a little bit vague here
通过利用多进程
but by leveraging multiple processes
你可以让内核
you can get the kernel
不执行一些可能导致panic的检查
to not perform some of the checks that would result in a panic
这绝对是值得考虑的
so that's something that is definitely worth considering
当你在遇到oops就panic的系统上
if you are trying to get a leak to defeat KASLR
尝试获得泄漏，以击败KASLR时
on a system that is configured to panic on oops
当你获得了内核泄漏
so once you've obtained a kernel leak
你想要做的下一件事是
the next thing that you want to be able to do is
确定你泄露的地址
to determine whether or not the address that you've leaked
是否对识别内核基址有用
is useful for identifying the kernel base address
可以用这个地址来击败KASLR吗
can I use this address to defeat KASLR
有几种方法可以做到这一点
and there's a couple ways that you could probably do this
我要展示的方式
but the way that I'm going to show
是利用GDB和ptdump插件
is to utilize GDB and the ptdump plugin
对你得到的值进行推理
to reason about the value that you've obtained
左边的终端在虚拟机里
so my terminal on the left hand side is inside the vm
右边的终端在虚拟机外
my terminal on the right hand side is outside of the vm
在这个演示中，我不会触发内核oops
now I'm not going to trigger a kernel oops for this demonstration
我把它留给学习者做练习
I'm going to leave the oopsing as an exercise for the learner
我们会
but we will instead
输出/proc/kallsyms
cat /proc/kallsyms
查找init_cred
and we will grep for a init_cred
我们假设这个是我们泄露的
and we'll pretend that this is our leak
输出kallsyms需要root权限
it is necessary to be root when you cat kallsyms
否则你得到的全是0，就像这里一样
or else you will get the zeros as you see right here
所以我们假设
so we'll pretend that
这个地址是我通过内核oops获得的
this address right here I've somehow managed to obtain via a kernel oops
或者其他类型的泄漏
or some other type of leak
一旦我完成泄露
now once I've done that
在虚拟机之外，我将运行sudo vm debug
outside of the vm I'm going to run sudo vm debug
一般来说，你不需要以root身份运行GDB
now generally speaking you don't need to run GDB as root
然而，为了能正常使用这个插件
however for this specific plugin to work correctly
你需要是root
you will want to be root
花点时间让GDB从内核加载符号
take a moment for GDB to load the symbols from the kernel
现在我们有一个调试器附加在
and now we have a debugger attached to the kernel
左边这个内核实例上
instance that's running on the left
我们可以展示这里启用了KASLR
now we can show that KASLR is enabled here
如果问GDB
because if we ask GDB
init_cred位于哪里
where is init_cred located
它会告诉我一个错误的地址
it's actually going to give me the wrong address
我们看到82a
we see 82a
而这里是a8e
and over here we see a8e
所以这些字节是随机化后的
and so these bytes are randomized
这就有点问题了
and so that is a bit of a problem
但是我们可以依靠/proc/kallsyms
but we can rely on /proc/kallsyms
来得到我们感兴趣的符号的地址
to get the address of symbols that we're interested in
所以
so
在调试时
while debugging that is
如果我想使用这个ptdump命令
so if I want to use this ptdump command
它位于dojo环境的
it is located on the dojo
它位于
it's located in
/opt/pt-dump
源代码文件
in the file that you are interested in sourcing
是pt.py
is pt.py
已经装在dojo环境了
so it's already there on the dojo
不用从github上pull
don't worry about trying to pull it in from github
要使用这个插件
to utilize the plugin
可以source 跟着文件路径
if the GDB prompt we can source that exact path
/opt/pt-dump /pt.py
/opt/pt-dump/pt.py
我们现在可以用PT命令了
we now have access to the PT command
你会注意到这输出了一堆内存区域
you'll notice that this outputs a bunch of regions of memory
该输出与gef中的vmmap命令非常相似
this output is very similar to the vmmap command from gef
不同之处在于vmmap只会显示用户空间地址
the difference is vmmap is going to show me user land addresses
ptdump将显示所有地址
where ptdump is going to show me all addresses
包括我们在这里看到的用户空间
including user space which we see right here
这里是正在使用的用户空间地址
and so here's the user space addresses that are in use
另一个值得注意的区域是physmap
another region that is notable here is physmap
我们可能与之互动过
which we may have interacted with
在pwn学院之前的一个模块中
in an earlier module here on pwn College
使用physmap可以做一些有趣的事情
there are some fun things to do with physmap
如果我们一直来到这个输出的最后
and if we get all the way back to the tail end of this output
我们可以看到内核在内存中的加载位置
we do see where the kernel is loaded in memory
我怎么知道我泄露的地址在哪里
so how do I know where my leak is
如果我们复制泄露的地址
if we copy our leak
我们可以使用PT命令
we can use the PT command
传给它 -has
and pass it has
然后接着我们感兴趣的地址
and then the address that we're interested in
ptdump会告诉我们
and ptdump will show us
这个地址或指针所对应的内存区域
the region of memory that this address or this pointer corresponds to
所以这个地址位于内核内存的这个区域
so this address is located in this region of the kernel's memory
下面我们可能想验证的是
now the next thing that we would probably want to verify is
这些内存区域是连续的吗
well is are these regions of memory contiguous
中间有空隙吗
are there gaps here
我们可以通过简单的计算来确定
and we can determine that by doing some pretty simple math here
如果我们从内核基址开始
if we start off with the kernel base address
然后加上第一个区域的大小
and then we add the size of this first region
然后加上第二个区域的大小
we could then add the size of the second region
然后加上第三个区域的大小
and then we could add the size of the third region
我想你知道这是怎么回事了
I think you see where this is going
然后加上第四个区域的大小
we're then going to include the size of the 4th region
现在只要这个加法的结果
now as long as the result of this addition
=
equals
第5个区域的起始地址
the starting address of the 5th region here
那么我们就知道这些都是连续内存
then we know this is all contiguous memory
这里加法的结果是
and what we see here is the result of the addition is
0x98ad 0000
98ad 0000
这就是内核最后一个内存区的基址
and that is the base address of this last section of the kernel
如果我们在往后一个内存区
now if we were to go one section further
我们看到结果是
we see
a9c 5个0
a9c and then five zeros
内核之后是什么呢
well what comes after the kernel
实际上是这个内核模块
well it's actually this kernel module
所以内核模块与内核并不相邻
and so kernel modules are not contiguous with the kernel
但所有内核中的地址都是连续的
but all addresses from the kernel are contiguous with the kernel
这意味着
so what that means
当我运行这个PT命令的时候
is when I run this PT has command
只要这里写的是kernel
as long as this section lists kernel
我们就知道我们在这五个内存区中的一个
then we know that we're in one of these five sections
还有这个地址有一个固定的偏移量
and the address should have a constant value or a constant offset
到内核的基址
to the base address of the kernel
我们可以计算出这个偏移值
we can compute that constant offset
只需要做一些简单的减法
by doing some simple subtraction
我们用设法获得的泄露地址
we'll take the leak that we've managed to obtain
减去
and then we will subtract
内核的基址
the base address of the kernel
就在这下面
I have it right down here
这就得到了一个神奇的常数
and that now gives me a magic constant
我们先来看看这个神奇的常数
we're just going to hang on to the magic constant for a moment
我们要证明
we want to prove
我们可以用这个偏移量
that we can use this offset
计算出代码的基址
to compute the base address of the code
所以我们退出GDB
so let's get out of GDB
重启虚拟机
let's vm restart
重启虚拟机的原因是
the reason I'm doing vm restart is because KASLR
KALSR只在启动时随机化
randomizes on boot
所以我现在重启虚拟机
so now what I'm doing is I'm rebooting the vm
这个重新随机化也会发生在
and this is the same type of re-randomization that would occur
你从练习模式
if you started off in practice mode
切换到挑战模式，应用你的利用脚本时
and then you wanted to apply your exploit in challenge mode
我们在这里做同样的事情
we'll do the same thing here
我左上角的终端
where my terminal on the upper left here
会连接上虚拟机
is going to connect to the vm
然后执行命令cat /proc/kallsyms
and we will sudo cat /proc/kallsyms
我们再次搜索init_cred
and we'll grep again for a init_cred
我们可以看到这里有bda
well we should see this has bytes bda
我们滑倒上面
we were to scroll up a little bit here
能看到确实变了
we see that it did change right
它随机化了
it has randomized
我要证明的是，用泄露的指针和计算出的常量
now my claim is by using my leaked pointer and our magic constant
我们可以预测
we can predict
内核的基址是什么
what the kernel base address will be
我们现在要验证这个
but we do need to be able to verify that
我们继续，sudo vm debug
so let's go ahead and sudo vm debug
我们将在GDB中进行计算
and we'll just do our math inside of GDB
我用泄露出的地址值
so if I take my leak that I somehow managed to obtain
减去
and then I subtract
我计算出的神奇常数
the magic constant that I've computed
这就是我计算出的
this is where I think
内核基址
the kernel base address is
我们引入ptdump
let's bring in ptdump
看看对不对
and let's see if we can be a little bit cheeky
我们用pt查看哪个内存区包含这个地址
and say what section contains this address
我们看到
and what we see
我预测的内核基址
is the address that I predicted to be the base address of the kernel
实际上位于可执行区
is in fact located in the executable section
能看到
which we saw
它是内核加载到的起始地址
was the beginning of where the kernel was loaded into memory
这证明我能计算出内核基址
so I was able to compute the base address of the kernel
一旦有了内核的基址
once I have the base address of the kernel
定位其他对象
locating other objects
或者感兴趣的内存地址
or interesting locations in memory
就和通过内存基址计算固定偏移量一样简单
is as easy as computing the magic offset from the base address of the kernel
到我感兴趣的点
to the point of interest that I am interested in
这适用于定位ROP gadget
that would apply to locating ROP gadgets
适用于定位数据段中感兴趣的区域
that would apply to locating interesting regions in the data segment
内核中的任何东西
anything in the kernel
都可以计算出来
can be computed
通过找到到内存基址的偏移量
by finding some magic constant to the base address of where the kernel is loaded into memory
希望这能给你们一些思路
so hopefully that gives you some idea of what to do
关于泄露了内存地址之后做什么
once you've managed to obtain a leak of kernel addresses